Guide to the John Lyons Papers TAM.025
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
John Lyons Papers
1905-1960
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Lyons, John, 1881-1957
Lyons, Mildred
TAM.025
1 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
John Lyons (1881-1957), socialist and labor leader, was a co-founder of the Rand School, and the Executive Secretary of the National Association of Retail Tailors, Cleaners and Dyers (NART), a National Recovery Act labor-management trade association. The collection contains correspondence relating to NART and related organizations, collective labor agreements for New York City locals of the Laundry Workers International Union, the 1906 minutes of the Daily Call Fair Committee, which organized a fair, presumably to raise funds for the 1908 launching of the New York Call, a socialist daily newspaper, material on Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring Branch 400 E, correspondence and other materials relating to the Reunion of Old Timers, an association of veteran members of the labor movement, correspondence and notes from Lyons' radio program on WEVD, correspondence relating to public programs sponsored by the Tamiment Institute, correspondence with the Liberal Party of New York State and the Socialist Party-Social Democratic Federation, and newspaper clippings by Lyons or relating to his political interests.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Mildred Lyons, widow of John Lyons, in 1957. The collection was transferred to New York University with the rest of the manuscript collections in the Tamiment Institute Library in 1963. The accession number 1963.004 is associated with this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
John Lyons (1881-1957), socialist and labor leader, was a co-founder of the Rand School, director of the Social Democratic Radio Forum on station WEVD, the New York radio station that had been established by the Socialist Party, a Socialist Party candidate for the New York State Legislature several times during the 1920s, and manager of the Zetex Corporation, a branch of the American Car and Foundry Company. Lyons was executive secretary of Branch 400 of the Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring, a Jewish fraternal organization then associated with the socialist movement, an organizer of the International Brotherhood of Pulp, Sulphite and Paper Mill Workers, chairman of the stabilization and control board of the Cleaners and Dryers of New York and assistant regional director of the Textile Workers Organizing Committee of New Jersey. In the mid-1930s, Lyons was the Executive Secretary of the National Association of Retail Tailors, Cleaners and Dyers, a National Recovery Act labor-management trade association.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence relating to the National Association of Retail Tailors, Cleaners and Dyers, the American Business Congress, the Independent Associated Service Industries, and the Service Trade League of New York, as well as collective labor agreements for New York City locals of the Laundry Workers International Union. Notable are the 1906 minutes of the Daily Call Fair Committee, which organized a fair, presumably to raise funds for the eventual 1908 launching of the New York Call, a socialist daily newspaper. In addition to minutes of Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring Branch 400 E, there is some correspondence and other material relating to the Reunion of Old Timers, an association of veteran members of the labor and social democratic movements; correspondence and notes from Lyon's radio program on WEVD; correspondence relating to public programs sponsored by the Tamiment Institute; correspondence with the Liberal Party of New York State and the Socialist Party-Social Democratic Federation; newspaper clippings by Lyons, including "Arrow Points," his column in The Social Democrat and clippings relating to his political interests.
Arrangement
The folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into one series:
Missing Title
I, Records, 1905-1960.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Records of the Reunion of Old Timers (TAM 283)
Radio broadcasting |z United States.; Socialists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Laundry workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Laundry industry |z New York (State) |z New York.; Jews |z New York (State) |z New York |x Societies, etc.; Fraternal organizations |z New York (State) |z New York.; Dry cleaning industry |z New York (State); Dry cleaning industry |x Employees |z United States.; Dry cleaning industry -- Employees -- New York (State); Correspondence.; Minutes (administrative records); Labor leaders -- New York (State); Clippings (information artifacts); Collective labor agreements.; Trade associations |z United States.; Lyons, John, 1881-1957; Socialist Party-Social Democratic Federation; Tamiment Institute; WEVD (Radio station) New York, N.Y.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring. Branch 400-E, New York (N.Y.); United States. National Recovery Administration; National Association of Retail Tailors, Cleaners and Dyers; Reunion of Old Timers; Service Trade League of New York; American Business Congress; Associated Service Industries; Cleaners and Dyers of New York; Daily Call Fair Committee; Independent Associated Service Industries; Laundry Workers International Union; Liberal Party of New York State; Lyons, Mildred
- Series I: Papers, 1905-1960.
  - American Business Congress: Clippings, Membership and Contacts Lists, 1941-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Business Congress: Correspondence, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arrow Points: John Lyons Column in The Social Democrat, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles, Letters to Editors, 1930s-1950s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Birthday, 70th, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings: National Association of Retail Tailors, Cleaners and Dyers, Inc. [John Lyons, Executive Secretary], 1932-1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Columbia University Course Records, 1910 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: General, Personal, 1922-1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Daily Call Fair Committee Minutes, Dec 1905-May 1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Laundry Workers' International Union., 1939[?] (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Liberal Party (New York State), 1949-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, 1924-1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National Association of Retail Tailors, Cleaners and Dyers, Inc.: Correspondence; Executive Board Minutes, Membership Lists, 1922-1934 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Old Age Magazine, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Reunion of Old Timers: Lehman Dinner, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Reunion of Old Timers: Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reunion of Old Timers: Walter Reuther Dinner, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Roosevelt/Lehman Election Campaign [John Lyons, Democratic Party State Committee; New York State Service Industries Committee], 1934-1936 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Service Industries (New York State), 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party, 1951, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Tamiment Institute, 1935, 1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - WEVD (Eugene Victor Debs): Correspondence, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - WEVD (Eugene Victor Debs): Notes for Programs, 1952-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - WEVD (Eugene Victor Debs): Notes for Programs, 1954-1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Workmen's Circle: Correspondence and Golden Anniversary Jubilee, 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Workmen's Circle: Branch 400-E: Minutes, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)